There's a man by the name of Captain
كان هناك رجل يدعى القائد
William Swenson
ويليام سونسون
who recently was awarded the congressional Medal of Honor
والذي تم توشيحه بوسام الشرف من الكونغرس
for his actions on September 8, 2009.
تكريما لأعماله في الثامن من سبتمبر 2009،
On that day, a column of American
في ذلك اليوم، كان فيلق من القوات
and Afghan troops
الأمريكية والأفغانية
were making their way
في طريقهم
through a part of Afghanistan
إلى منطقة في أفغانستان
to help protect
للمساعدة على حماية
a group of government officials,
مجموعة من المسؤولين الحكوميين،
a group of Afghan government officials,
مجموعة من المسؤولين الحكوميين الأفغانيين،
who would be meeting with some local
الذين كانوا سيلتقون ببعض
village elders.
شيوخ بعض القرى المحلية.
The column came under ambush,
سقط الفيلق في كمين،
and was surrounded on three sides,
وتمت محاصرتهم من ثلاث جهات،
and amongst many other things,
ومن ضمن عدة إنجازات،
Captain Swenson was recognized
تم تكريم القائد سونسون
for running into live fire
على اقتحامه لإطلاق نار حي
to rescue the wounded
لإنقاذ الجرحى
and pull out the dead.
وإخراج الموتى.
One of the people he rescued was a sergeant,
من بين الناس الذين أنقذهم كان هناك رقيب،
and he and a comrade were making their way
كان هو وأحد رفاقه يحاولون الوصول
to a medevac helicopter.
إلى مروحية الإخلاء الطبي.
And what was remarkable about this day
وما كان ملفتا ذلك اليوم،
is, by sheer coincidence,
أنه وبالصدفة المحضة،
one of the medevac medics
أحد أفراد طاقم الإخلاء الطبي
happened to have a GoPro camera on his helmet
كان يلبس خوذة بها كاميرا GoPro
and captured the whole scene on camera.
فحصل أن صور المشهد كله بهذه الكاميرا.
It shows Captain Swenson and his comrade
أظهرت الصور القائد سونسون ورفيقه
bringing this wounded soldier
وهما يحملان ذلك الجندي المجروح
who had received a gunshot to the neck.
الذي أصيب بطلق ناري في رقبته.
They put him in the helicopter,
وضعوه داخل المروحية،
and then you see Captain Swenson bend over
وفي تلك اللحظة ترى القائد سونسون وقد انحنى
and give him a kiss
ليقبله
before he turns around to rescue more.
قبل أن يستدير لينقذ المزيد من الجنود.
I saw this, and I thought to myself,
رأيت هذا، فتساءلت،
where do people like that come from?
من أين يأتي أناس مثل هؤلاء؟
What is that? That is some deep, deep emotion,
ما كان هذا؟ مشاعر عميقة، عميقة جدا،
when you would want to do that.
تجعلك تريد القيام بهذا.
There's a love there,
كان هناك حب،
and I wanted to know why is it that
فأردت أن أعرف لماذا
I don't have people that I work with like that?
ليس لدي زملاء مثل هؤلاء؟
You know, in the military, they give medals
أتعلمون، في الجيش، يمنحون ميداليات
to people who are willing to sacrifice themselves
للأشخاص المستعدين للتضحية بأنفسهم،
so that others may gain.
لكي يفوز الآخرون.
In business, we give bonuses to people
في مجال الأعمال، نعطي منحا لأشخاص
who are willing to sacrifice others
مستعدين للتضحية بالآخرين
so that we may gain.
لعلنا نفوز.
We have it backwards. Right?
نتعامل مع الأشياء بالمقلوب، أليس كذلك؟
So I asked myself, where do people like this come from?
فتساءلت، من أين يأتي أناس مثل هؤلاء؟
And my initial conclusion was that they're just better people.
فكان استنتاجي الأولي أنهم كانوا أشخاصا أفضل.
That's why they're attracted to the military.
لذلك انجذبوا إلى المجال العسكري.
These better people are attracted
ينجذب الأشخاص المتميزون
to this concept of service.
إلى مفهوم الخدمة هذا.
But that's completely wrong.
لكن هذا التفسير خاطىء تماما.
What I learned was that it's the environment,
ما تعلمته هو أن الأمر متعلق بالمحيط،
and if you get the environment right,
إذا كانت لديك بيئة مناسبة،
every single one of us has the capacity
ستكون لكل واحد منا القدرة
to do these remarkable things,
على القيام بأشياء مميزة،
and more importantly, others have that capacity too.
والأمر الأهم، هو أن الجميع يمكنهم القيام بهذا أيضا.
I've had the great honor of getting to meet
كان لي عظيم الشرف أن حظيت بلقاء
some of these, who we would call heroes,
أحد هؤلاء، الذين نسميهم أبطالا،
who have put themselves and put their lives
الذين خاطروا بأنفسهم وحياتهم
at risk to save others,
من أجل إنقاذ الآخرين،
and I asked them, "Why would you do it?
فسألتهم " لماذا تقومون بذلك؟"
Why did you do it?"
"لماذا قمتم بذلك؟"
And they all say the same thing:
فكان أن كانت إجابتهم واحدة:
"Because they would have done it for me."
"لأنهم كانوا ليقوموا بذلك من أجلي أيضا."
It's this deep sense of trust and cooperation.
إنه ذلك الشعور العميق بالثقة والتعاون.
So trust and cooperation are really important here.
لذا فالثقة والتعاون مهمان جدا هنا.
The problem with concepts of trust and cooperation
الإشكال المطروح بخصوص هذين المفهومين
is that they are feelings, they are not instructions.
أنهما عبارة عن مشاعر، وليس أوامر.
I can't simply say to you, "Trust me," and you will.
لا يمكنني أن أقول لك ببساطة "ثق بي"، فتفعل.
I can't simply instruct two people to cooperate, and they will.
لا يمكنني ببساطة أن آمر شخصين بالتعاون، فيفعلان.
It's not how it works. It's a feeling.
لا تسير الأمور على هذا النحو. إنها مشاعر.
So where does that feeling come from?
إذن فمن أين تأتي المشاعر؟
If you go back 50,000 years
إذا عدت إلى الماضي ب50 ألف سنة،
to the Paleolithic era,
إلى العصر الحجري،
to the early days of Homo sapiens,
إلى المراحل الأولى لظهور الإنسان العاقل،
what we find is that the world
ما سنجده أن العالم كان
was filled with danger,
مليئا بالمخاطر،
all of these forces working very, very hard to kill us.
كانت كل تلك القوى تعمل كل ما بوسعها لتقتلنا.
Nothing personal.
ليس الأمر شخصيا.
Whether it was the weather,
سواء تعلق الأمر بالطقس،
lack of resources,
أوندرة المصادر،
maybe a saber-toothed tiger,
أو النمر الحاد الأنياب،
all of these things working
كل تلك العوامل كانت تعمل
to reduce our lifespan.
لتنقص أمد حياتنا.
And so we evolved into social animals,
فكان أن تطورنا لنصبح حيوانات اجتماعية،
where we lived together and worked together
نعيش ونعمل معا،
in what I call a circle of safety, inside the tribe,
داخل ما أسميه دائرة الأمان، في كنف القبيلة،
where we felt like we belonged.
حيث شعرنا بالانتماء.
And when we felt safe amongst our own,
وحين أحسسنا بالأمان مع بعضنا،
the natural reaction was trust and cooperation.
كانت النتيجة الطبيعية عبارة عن الثقة والتعاون
There are inherent benefits to this.
كانت هناك فوائد
It means I can fall asleep at night
مما يعني أنني أستطيع أن أنام ليلا
and trust that someone from within my tribe will watch for danger.
وأنا واثق أن هناك أحد من القبيلة يقوم بالحراسة.
If we don't trust each other, if I don't trust you,
إن لم نثق ببعضنا، إن لم أكن أثق بك،
that means you won't watch for danger.
هذا يعني أنك لن تحميني من المخاطر.
Bad system of survival.
منظومة بقاء غير جيدة.
The modern day is exactly the same thing.
هذا ما نعيشه تماما اليوم.
The world is filled with danger,
العالم مليء بالمخاطر اليوم،
things that are trying to frustrate our lives
أشياء تحاول تقويض عيشنا
or reduce our success,
تقليص نجاحنا،
reduce our opportunity for success.
تقليص فرص نجاحنا.
It could be the ups and downs in the economy,
قد تكون تقلبات الاقتصاد،
the uncertainty of the stock market.
أو تقلبات سوق الأسهم.
It could be a new technology that renders
قد تكون التكنولوجيا التي تجعل
your business model obsolete overnight.
من نظام عملك منتهي الصلاحية بين عشية وضحاها.
Or it could be your competition
أو قد يكون منافسوك
that is sometimes trying to kill you.
الذين يحاولون في بعض الأحيان قتلك.
It's sometimes trying to put you out of business,
أو أن يخرجوك من مجال الأعمال،
but at the very minimum
أو على الأقل،
is working hard to frustrate your growth
يحاولون جاهدين أن يعيقوا تقدمك
and steal your business from you.
أو سرقة فكرة أعمالك منك.
We have no control over these forces.
لا يمكننا أن نتحكم بهذه القوى.
These are a constant,
هذه معطيات واقعية،
and they're not going away.
ولا يمكنها أن تختفي.
The only variable are the conditions
المتغير الوحيد هي ظروف العمل
inside the organization,
داخل المؤسسات،
and that's where leadership matters,
وهنا حيث تبدو أهمية القيادة،
because it's the leader that sets the tone.
لأن القائد هو من يفرض جو العمل.
When a leader makes the choice
حين يختار قائد ما
to put the safety and lives
أن يضع سلامة وحياة
of the people inside the organization first,
الناس داخل المؤسسة أولا،
to sacrifice their comforts and sacrifice
وأن يضحي براحتهم
the tangible results, so that the people remain
وبالنتائج الملموسة لكي يبقى الناس
and feel safe and feel like they belong,
لكي يشعروا بالأمان وبالانتماء،
remarkable things happen.
حينها يمكن لأشياء مميزة أن تحدث.
I was flying on a trip,
كنت في رحلة جوية،
and I was witness to an incident
وكنت شاهدا على حادث
where a passenger attempted to board
حيث حاول مسافر الصعود إلى الطائرة
before their number was called,
قبل أن ينادى عليه،
and I watched the gate agent
ورأيت المسؤولة على البوابة
treat this man like he had broken the law,
وهي تعامل الرجل على أنه خارق للقانون،
like a criminal.
على أنه مجرم.
He was yelled at for attempting to board
صُرخ في وجهه لأنه حاول إركاب
one group too soon.
مجموعة قبل الوقت المحدد.
So I said something.
فقلت شيئا.
I said, "Why do you have treat us like cattle?
قلت: "لم عليك أن تعامليننا على أننا قطيع؟
Why can't you treat us like human beings?"
لم لا يمكنك أن تعاملينا على أننا بشر؟"
And this is exactly what she said to me.
فكان هذا ما قالته لي بالضبط.
She said, "Sir, if I don't follow the rules,
قالت "سيدي، إن لم أتبع القوانين،
I could get in trouble or lose my job."
فسأقع في مشاكل أو سيتم طردي من العمل."
All she was telling me
كل ما كانت تخبرني به
is that she doesn't feel safe.
أنها لم تكن تشعر بالأمان.
she doesn't trust her leaders.
أنها لم تكن تثق بقادتها.
The reason we like flying Southwest Airlines
السبب الذي يجعلنا نسافر على خطوط ساوث ويست
is not because they necessarily hire better people.
ليس لأنها بالضرورة تشغل أفضل الطواقم.
It's because they don't fear their leaders.
بل لأنهم لا يخشون مدراءهم.
You see, if the conditions are wrong,
أرأيتم، إذا كانت الظروف غير جيدة،
we are forced to expend our own time and energy
فإننا نكون مجبرين على بذل وقتنا وطاقتنا
to protect ourselves from each other,
لحماية أنفسنا من بعضنا البعض،
and that inherently weakens the organization.
وهذا يضعف مؤسستنا من الداخل.
When we feel safe inside the organization,
عندما نحس بالأمان داخل مؤسستنا،
we will naturally combine our talents
نستجمع بشكل طبيعي مواهبنا،
and our strengths and work tirelessly
وقوانا وعملنا بدون كلل
to face the dangers outside
لنواجه المخاطر الخارجية
and seize the opportunities.
ونغتم الفرص المتاحة.
The closest analogy I can give
أقرب تشبيه يمكنني أن أعطيه
to what a great leader is, is like being a parent.
لما قد يكون عليه القائد الجيد، هو الأب.
If you think about what being a great parent is,
إذا فكرت في ما قد يكون عليه الأب الجيد،
what do you want? What makes a great parent?
ما الذي تريده؟ ماهي صفات الأب الجيد؟
We want to give our child opportunities,
نريد أن نمنح لأطفالنا فرصا،
education, discipline them when necessary,
نربيهم ونؤدبهم إذا اقتضى الحال،
all so that they can grow up and achieve more
كل ذلك من أجل أن يكبروا ويحققوا أكثر
than we could for ourselves.
مما حققناه نحن.
Great leaders want exactly the same thing.
يريد القادة العظماء نفس الشيء.
They want to provide their people opportunity,
يريدون أن يمنحوا فرصا لموظفيهم،
education, discipline when necessary,
أن يوفروا لهم تربية وتأديبا إن اقتضى الأمر،
build their self-confidence, give them the opportunity to try and fail,
لبناء ثقة بأنفسهم، وإعطائهم فرصة لكي يحاولوا ويفشلوا،
all so that they could achieve more
كل ذلك من أجل أن يحققوا أكثر
than we could ever imagine for ourselves.
مما كنا نتخيل أن نحققه بأنفسنا.
Charlie Kim, who's the CEO of a company called Next Jump
شارلي كيم، المدير التنفيذي لشركة تدعى "نيكست جامب"
in New York City, a tech company,
بمدينة نيويروك، وهي شركة تكنولوجيا،
he makes the point that
أشار شارلي إلى نقطة مهمة حين تساءل
if you had hard times in your family,
إن كنت تمر بظروف صعبة مع عائلتك
would you ever consider laying off one of your children?
فهل سيخطر ببالك قط أن تتخلى عن أحد أبنائك؟
We would never do it.
لم نكن لنقوم بهذا أبدا.
Then why do we consider laying off people
إذا لماذا نفكر في إمكانية التخلي عن موظفينا
inside our organization?
في المؤسسات؟
Charlie implemented a policy
طبق شارلي قانون
of lifetime employment.
التوظيف مدى الحياة.
If you get a job at Next Jump,
إذا كنت تعمل لدى "نيكست جامب"
you cannot get fired for performance issues.
فلن يتم تسريحك بسبب مشاكل في أدائك.
In fact, if you have issues,
بل بالعكس، إن كانت لديك مشاكل
they will coach you and they will give you support,
فإنهم سيدربونك ويدعمونك،
just like we would with one of our children
تماما كما كنا سنقوم بفعله مع أحد أبنائنا
who happens to come home with a C from school.
حين يعود إلى البيت حاملا نقطة امتحان "ج".
It's the complete opposite.
ما يحصل هو العكس تماما.
This is the reason so many people
لهذا السبب يحمل العديد من الناس
have such a visceral hatred, anger,
ذلك الكره الشديد والغضب
at some of these banking CEOs
من بعض أأولئك المدراء التنفيذيين للأبناك
with their disproportionate salaries and bonus structures.
نظرا لرواتبهم ونظم منحهم غير المتكافئة.
It's not the numbers.
لا يتعلق الأمر هنا بالأرقام.
It's that they have violated the very definition of leadership.
بل لخرقهم السافر لتعريف القيادة.
They have violated this deep-seated social contract.
لقد خرقوا هذا العقد الضارب بعمقه في المجتمع.
We know that they allowed their people
نعلم أنهم سمحوا لموظفيهم بالتضحية
to be sacrificed so they could protect their own interests,
بأنفسهم لكي يحموا مصالحهم.
or worse, they sacrificed their people
بل الأدهى، أنهم ضحوا بموظفيهم
to protect their own interests.
لحماية مصالحهم الشخصية.
This is what so offends us, not the numbers.
وهذا ما يزعجنا جدا، وليست الأرقام.
Would anybody be offended if we gave
هل منا من كان سينزعج إن أعطينا
a $150 million bonus to Gandhi?
غاندي 100 مليون دولار كمنحة؟
How about a $250 million bonus to Mother Teresa?
ماذا عن 250 ميليون دولار للأم تيريزا؟
Do we have an issue with that? None at all.
هل سيكون لدينا أي مانع؟ إطلاقا.
None at all.
إطلاقا.
Great leaders would never sacrifice
لم يكن القادة العظماء ليضحوا أبدا
the people to save the numbers.
بموظفيهم من أجل إنقاذ أرباحهم.
They would sooner sacrifice the numbers
بل كانوا ليضحوا بأرباحهم
to save the people.
لإنقاذ موظفيهم.
Bob Chapman, who runs
بوب شابمان، الذي كان يدير
a large manufacturing company in the Midwest
مصنعا كبيرا في الغرب الأوسط
called Barry-Wehmiller,
يدعى باري- ويميلير،
in 2008 was hit very hard by the recession,
والذي تأثر بشكل كبير بالانكماش الاقتصادي سنة 2008،
and they lost 30 percent of their orders overnight.
وبين عشية وضحاها، خسروا 30% من الطلبات.
Now in a large manufacturing company,
في حالة شركة صناعية كبيرة،
this is a big deal,
فإن هذا الأمر يعتبر مشكلا كبيرا،
and they could no longer afford their labor pool.
وقد يجعلهم هذا غير قادرين على تحمل مصاريف عمالهم.
They needed to save 10 million dollars,
كان عليهم ادخار 10 ملايين دولار،
so, like so many companies today,
لذا، كما هو الحال بالنسبة للعديد من الشركات اليوم،
the board got together and discussed layoffs.
اجتمع مجلس الإدارة لمناقشة تسريح العمال.
And Bob refused.
لكن بوب رفض.
You see, Bob doesn't believe in head counts.
أرأيتم، لا يؤمن بوب باليد العاملة.
Bob believes in heart counts,
يؤمن بوب بالقلب العامل.
and it's much more difficult to simply reduce
والأمر أصعب من أن يتم ببساطة
the heart count.
تسريح قلب عامل.
And so they came up with a furlough program.
لذا فقد خرجوا ببرنامج إجازات.
Every employee, from secretary to CEO,
كل موظف بدءً من السكرتيرة إلى المدير التنفيذي،
was required to take four weeks of unpaid vacation.
كان مطالبا بأخذ4 أسابيع كعطلة غير مدفوعة الأجر.
They could take it any time they wanted,
يمكنهم أخذها في أي وقت شاؤوا،
and they did not have to take it consecutively.
وكان عليهم أن لا يأخذوها بالتتابع.
But it was how Bob announced the program
لكن كانت الطريقة التي أعلن بها بوب هذا البرنامج
that mattered so much.
هي التي أحدثت الفرق.
He said, it's better that we should all suffer a little
فقد قال، سيكون من الأفضل أن نتألم كلنا قليلا
than any of us should have to suffer a lot,
على أن يتألم بعض منا بشكل كبير،
and morale went up.
فارتفعت معنويات الموظفين.
They saved 20 million dollars,
بذلك ادخروا 20 مليون دولار،
and most importantly, as would be expected,
والأهم من هذا، كما كان متوقعا،
when the people feel safe and protected by the leadership in the organization,
عندما شعر الناس بالأمان والحماية من طرف مدرائهم
the natural reaction is to trust and cooperate.
كانت ردة الفعل الطبيعية هي الثقة والتعاون.
And quite spontaneously, nobody expected,
وبشكل متزامن وغير متوقع،
people started trading with each other.
بدأ الناس في التبادل فيما بينهم
Those who could afford it more
من كان يستطيع التحمل أكثر
would trade with those who could afford it less.
كان ليتبادل مع من كان يستطيع التحمل بشكل أقل،
People would take five weeks
كان بعضهم يأخذ 5 أسابيع
so that somebody else only had to take three.
لكي يأخذ الآخرون 3 أسابيع فقط.
Leadership is a choice. It is not a rank.
القيادة هي اختيار، وليست رتبة.
I know many people at the seniormost
أعرف كثيرا من الأشخاص في أعلى
levels of organizations
المراتب في مؤسساتهم
who are absolutely not leaders.
من ليسوا بقادة مطلقا.
They are authorities, and we do what they say
هم قوى نافذة، ونحن نطبق ما يقولون
because they have authority over us,
لأن لديهم سلطة علينا،
but we would not follow them.
لكن لم نكن لنتبعهم.
And I know many people
وأعرف أشخاصا
who are at the bottoms of organizations
ممن هم في قاعدة هرم مؤسساتهم
who have no authority
ليست لديهم أية سلطة
and they are absolutely leaders,
لكنهم قادة حقيقيون،
and this is because they have chosen to look after
ذلك لأنهم اختاروا أن يعتنوا
the person to the left of them,
بالشخص على يسارهم،
and they have chosen to look after
ولأنهم اختاروا أن يعتنوا
the person to the right of them.
بالشخص على يمينهم.
This is what a leader is.
وهذا ما تعنيه كلمة قائد.
I heard a story
سمعت قصة
of some Marines
لبعض مشاة البحرية
who were out in theater,
الذين ذهبوا إلى أحد المسارح،
and as is the Marine custom,
وكما هي عادة مشاة البحرية
the officer ate last,
كان الضابط آخر من أكل،
and he let his men eat first,
وجعل فريقه يأكلون أولا،
and when they were done,
وحين انتهوا،
there was no food left for him.
لم يتبق طعام له،
And when they went back out in the field,
وحين عادوا إلى الميدان،
his men brought him some of their food
أحضر له رجاله بعضا من طعامهم
so that he may eat,
لعله يأكله،
because that's what happens.
لأن هذا ما يحدث.
We call them leaders because they go first.
نسميهم قادة لأنهم هم من يكونون بالمقدمة.
We call them leaders because they take the risk
نسميهم قادة لأنهم يخاطرون
before anybody else does.
قبل الجميع.
We call them leaders because they will choose
نسميهم قادة لأنهم يختارون
to sacrifice so that their people
أن يضحوا لكي ينعم موظفوهم
may be safe and protected
بالأمان والحماية
and so their people may gain,
ولكي يستفيدوا،
and when we do, the natural response
وحين نقوم بهذا، تكون النتيجة الطبيعية
is that our people will sacrifice for us.
أن فريقنا سيضحي من أجلنا.
They will give us their blood and sweat and tears
سيهدوننا دمهم وعرقهم ودموعهم
to see that their leader's vision comes to life,
لكي يروا أن رؤية قادتهم رأت النور،
and when we ask them, "Why would you do that?
وحين نسألهم،"لم تقومون بهذا؟
Why would you give your blood and sweat and tears
لم تعطون دمكم وعرقكم ودموعكم
for that person?" they all say the same thing:
لذلك الشخص؟" سيكون جوابهم واحدا:
"Because they would have done it for me."
"لأنهم كانوا ليقوموا بهذا من أجلي."
And isn't that the organization
أليست هذه هي المؤسسة التي
we would all like to work in?
نود جميعا العمل فيها؟
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)